Guide to the American Association of Political Consultants interview collection, 1997-1999 MS2100
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
American Association of Political Consultants interview collection
1996-2000 and undated
1996-2000
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
American Association of Political Consultants
MS2100
2 Linear Feet Two linear feet and 24 digital objects.
This collection consists of interviews with 15 political consultants, one tape of political commercials, and transcriptions of these materials. The videotapes include oral history interviews conducted by John Franzen, Whit Ayres, and others with political consultants including Charlie Black, Jill Buckley, Joe Cerrell, Wally Clinton, Walter DeVries, Bob Goodman, Charles Guggenheim, Bill Hamilton, Peter Hart, Joe Napolitan, Matt Reese, Stuart Spencer, Ray Strother, Robert M. Teeter, and Richard Wirthlin.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
The American Association of Political Consultants (AAPC) is the professional organization for people working in the field of politics in the United States. They have joined together to promote the following goals: to raise the standards of practice in political consultation, thereby enhancing the political process and improving public confidence in the American political system; to provide professional guidance, assistance, and education to members as they develop the skills, techniques, and business procedures required for successful political consultation; to establish and maintain a high standard of ethical conduct through membership education and the establishment and promotion of a workable Code of Professional Ethics for members; to help inform the news media, educational institutions, political organizations, and the general public about the value of political consultation and its contribution to the political process; and to place particular emphasis in our work on reaching out to involve and educate young people in the art of political consultation and in the benefits it brings to the practice of democracy.
The American Association of Political Consultants, founded in 1969, is a bipartisan organization of political professionals. Association membership consists of political consultants, media consultants, pollsters, campaign managers, corporate public affairs officers, professors, fund-raisers, lobbyists, congressional staffers and vendors and is open to everyone associated with politics from the local level to the White House. AAPC members understand that, while they are often competitors on election day, they are all colleagues with similar professional concerns that transcend "Republican", "Democrat" or "Independent" labels.
The creation of political consultation as a separate career discipline has been a development of the middle 20th Century. As with most of politics, there is disagreement over when the "industry" began. Some call the California firms of Baus and Ross or Whittaker-Baxter, back in the 1930s, the founders of the field. Others credit people like Joe Napolitan, Clif White, Matt Reese, Bill Roberts, Stu Spencer, Joe Cerrell, Bill Hamilton, Bob Squier, Walter deVries and their peers as the first "true" political consultants. These political pioneers date back to the 1950s.
Political consultants can do everything or specialize in one specific service. General services include overall strategic expertise, whereas specialist services include such diverse talents as survey research, television or radio production and placement, telemarketing, direct mail, fund raising, media relations, computer use, and a host of additional forms of expertise.
Political advice-giving as a business, independent of other types of income production, began about the same time as the formation of the American Association of Political Consultants in 1969. Only a handful of people attended the first meeting at Lincoln Center in New York City. The association now numbers more than 1,100 active members, and operates from a permanent office in Washington, D.C.
The American Association of Political Consultants maintains a Code of Professional Ethics for members.
From the AAPC's website 2005.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of interviews with 15 political consultants, one tape of political commercials, and transcriptions of these materials. The videotapes include oral history interviews conducted by John Franzen, Whit Ayres, and others with political consultants including Charlie Black, Jill Buckley, Joe Cerrell, Wally Clinton, Walter DeVries, Bob Goodman, Charles Guggenheim, Bill Hamilton, Peter Hart, Joe Napolitan, Matt Reese, Stuart Spencer, Ray Strother, Robert M. Teeter, and Richard Wirthlin.
Politics and government; Washington (D.C.); Political consultants; Oral history; Ethics; Teeter, Robert M.; Wirthlin, Richard; De Vries, Walter; Black, Charles R.; Cerrell, Joseph; Strother, Raymond; Guggenheim, Charles
- Interviews on videocassette, 1996-2000 and undated; MS2100 Series 1; 2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains videotapes of oral history interviews conducted with political consultants. It includes interviews on VHS cassettes and master tapes on Beta and Umatic cassettes. The interviews date from 1996-2000 or are undated. The videotapes include oral history interviews conducted by John Franzen, Whit Ayres, and others with political consultants including Charlie Black, Jill Buckley, Joe Cerrell, Wally Clinton, Walter DeVries, Bob Goodman, Charles Guggenheim, Bill Hamilton, Peter Hart, Joe Napolitan, Matt Reese, Stuart Spencer, Ray Strother, Robert M. Teeter, and Richard Wirthlin.
  - Interview: Bob Teeter w/Whit Ayres, Atlanta, GA Tape 1, 2000 January 16 (Box 1, Videocassette 1)
  - Interview: Bob Teeter w/Whit Ayres, Atlanta, GA Tape 2, 2000 January 16 (Box 1, Videocassette 2)
  - Interview: Bob Teeter w/Whit Ayres, Atlanta, GA Tape 3, 2000 January 16 (Box 1, Videocassette 3)
  - Dr. Richard Wirthlin Interview by Whit Ayres TRT 1:20:00, 1999 December 09 (Box 1, Videocassette 4)
  - Alfano Fremont-Smith American Association of Political Consultants Interview W/Charlie Black, Republicans General Consultants Tape 1 of 2, 1999 October 25 (Box 1, Videocassette 5)
  - Alfano Fremont-Smith American Association of Political Consultants Interview W/Charlie Black, Republicans General Consultants Tape 2 of 2, 1999 October 25 (Box 1, Videocassette 6)
  - Interview with Jill Buckley by John Franzen, 1997 August 25 (Box 2, Videocassette 1)
  - Interview with Joe Cerrell by John Franzen, 1997 October 24 (Box 2, Videocassette 2)
  - Interview with Wally Clinton by John Franzen, 1997 December 22 (Box 2, Videocassette 3)
  - Interview with Walter DeVries by John Franzen, 1997 November 07 (Box 2, Videocassette 4)
  - Interview with Charles Guggenheim by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1997 July 20 (Box 2, Videocassette 5)
  - Interview with Charles Guggenheim by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1997 July 20 (Box 2, Videocassette 6)
  - Interview with Bill Hamilton by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1996 December 12 (Box 3, Videocassette 1)
  - Interview with Bill Hamilton by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1996 December 12 (Box 3, Videocassette 2)
  - Interview with Peter Hart by John Franzen Tape 1 of 1, 1997 December 22 (Box 3, Videocassette 3)
  - Interview with Joe Napolitan by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1996 December 03 (Box 3, Videocassette 4)
  - Interview with Joe Napolitan by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1996 December 03 (Box 3, Videocassette 5)
  - Interview with Matt Reese by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1996 December 12 (Box 3, Videocassette 6)
  - Interview with Matt Reese by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1996 December 12 (Box 4, Videocassette 1)
  - Interview with Ray Strother by John Franzen Tape 1 of 1, 1997 October 10 (Box 4, Videocassette 2)
  - American Association of Political Consultants Wayne C. Johnson & Associates, Inc. "Interview With Bob Goodman" TRT -- 1:18:18, 1999 October 25 (Box 4, Videocassette 3)
  - AAPC -- Stu Spencer Tape #1, 1999 January 01 (Box 4, Videocassette 4)
  - AAPC -- Stu Spencer Tape #2, 1999 January 01 (Box 4, Videocassette 5)
  - American Association of Political Consultants Commercials TRT 8:18, undated (Box 4, Videocassette 6)
  - Interviews--master tapes: Beta and Umatic, undated (Box 5)
- Interview transcripts, 1996-2000 and undated; MS2100 Series 2; 24 digital object(s)
  This series contains transcripts of oral history interviews conducted with political consultants. The interviews date from 1996-2000 or are undated. The transcripts include oral history interviews conducted by John Franzen, Whit Ayres, and others with political consultants including Charlie Black, Jill Buckley, Joe Cerrell, Wally Clinton, Walter DeVries, Bob Goodman, Charles Guggenheim, Bill Hamilton, Peter Hart, Joe Napolitan, Matt Reese, Stuart Spencer, Ray Strother, Robert M. Teeter, and Richard Wirthlin.
  Existence and Location of Originals
  These items are stored offline and will require staff assistance to access.
  - Transcript of interview: Bob Teeter w/Whit Ayres, Atlanta, GA Tape 1, 2000 January 16
    This item is stored offline and will require staff assistance to access.
  - Transcript of interview: Bob Teeter w/Whit Ayres, Atlanta, GA Tape 2, 2000 January 16
  - Transcript of interview: Bob Teeter w/Whit Ayres, Atlanta, GA Tape 3, 2000 January 16
  - Transcript of Dr. Richard Wirthlin Interview by Whit Ayres TRT 1:20:00, 1999 December 09
  - Transcript of Alfano Fremont-Smith American Association of Political Consultants Interview w/Charlie Black, Republicans General Consultants Tape 1 of 2, 1999 October 25
  - Transcript of Alfano Fremont-Smith American Association of Political Consultants Interview w/Charlie Black, Republicans General Consultants Tape 1 of 2, 1999 October 25
  - Transcript of interview with Jill Buckley by John Franzen, 1997 August 25
  - Transcript of interview with Joe Cerrell by John Franzen, 1997 October 24
  - Transcript of interview with Wally Clinton by John Franzen, 1997 December 22
  - Transcript of interview with Walter DeVries by John Franzen, 1997 November 07
  - Transcript of interview with Charles Guggenheim by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1997 July 20
  - Transcript of interview with Charles Guggenheim by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1997 July 20
  - Transcript of interview with Bill Hamilton by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1996 December 12
  - Transcript of interview with Bill Hamilton by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1996 December 12
  - Transcript of interview with Peter Hart by John Franzen Tape 1 of 1, 1997 December 22
  - Transcript of interview with Joe Napolitan by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1996 December 03
  - Transcript of interview with Joe Napolitan by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1996 December 03
  - Transcript of interview with Matt Reese by John Franzen Tape 1 of 2, 1996 December 12
  - Transcript of interview with Matt Reese by John Franzen Tape 2 of 2, 1996 December 12
  - Transcript of interview with Ray Strother by John Franzen Tape 1 of 1, 1997 October 10
  - Transcript of American Association of Political Consultants Wayne C. Johnson & Associates, Inc. "Interview With Bob Goodman" TRT -- 1:18:18, 1999 October 25
  - Transcript of AAPC -- Stu Spencer Tape #1, 1999 January 01
  - Transcript of AAPC -- Stu Spencer Tape #2, 1999 January 01
  - Transcript of American Association of Political Consultants Commercials TRT 8:18, undated